Hi. Uh, and admitting everybody from
the, uh, waiting room. So, we'll just
give people a minute to come on in from
the waiting room. Usually takes a minute
or so for that to happen. [snorts] Our
recording has started. So, just as a
reminder to everybody who is here on the
meeting, we do record these sessions,
these meetings. So, uh, they do get
posted to the the program website. Um so
please remember to keep your language
appropriate for a broader and wide
audience. Um and so this is the end of
life care committee with uh Dr. Larry
Leman as the chair. Uh I am Dr. Dominic
Zerlo from the New Mexico Department of
Health Center for Medical Cannabis and
Psilocybin. But I'm really here just to
help answer questions and our team is
here from the department to help with
the logistics and to hear really what
everybody has to say. And so with that,
I turn it over to you, Larry, and it is
your meeting.
>> Great. Thanks, Tom. Thanks, everybody.
Um, thanks for everybody's uh who's was
on the meeting last week when we had the
tech problems and coming back. So,
appreciate that. Um, the um today is
going to our goal is going to be focused
on what end of life competencies, you
know, what do we think people, you know,
need to have for as a background? what
does that mean as far as if it's
didactic hours, if it's practicum or
different courses. So, I'm going to do
some slides but a little bit of overview
for context and then Jen Kman's going to
do a presentation on the competencies
and then um I'll facilitate a discussion
on how that can play out in practicum
and um we have a couple of people that
Mary Kosamano is should be joining us.
She's um uh has a long history of being
a a researcher of end of life from um
Maryland and John's Hopkins. So Mary
will be uh joining uh joining us and
Michael Williams is here too. Michael
has um a long history of being involved
with end of life care and um you know
the spiritual aspect. We're really happy
to have uh have everybody here.
So um just just I like to start sort of
like with the overview of how we've
established with the end of life
committee what are our core sort of
areas here which are seven of them and
the ones that are kind of relevant to
today is like therapeutic team
development and educational workforce
development.
Um and you know again just as a little
bit of a reminder and approach here that
end of life care is different from the
other indications as a stage of life and
a disease diagnosis. Um previous from
previous recommendations for the film
was that end of life um psychedelic care
team should have at least 15 to 20 hours
of training specific to this area. And
we'll talk about how that fits in and it
kind of fits into the discussion that's
happening tomorrow at the board meeting
as well as the uh training committee
meeting. and that the spiritual care
component to be offered and supported
when desired.
Um that when we look at the team
development and competencies, it extends
beyond a strictly medical provider and
licensed therapist model to include
nurses, social workers, other
professionals as well as emerging roles
such as psychedelic end of life duelist
and chaplain both of who have done
presentations to the committee in the
past few months.
can skip this slide
and we can skip that slide too.
So one other thing to remember as we're
talking thinking about competencies is
we have described a role for the space
attendant um um which is both an acronym
and it also talks about holding um
holding space which we think may be
particularly important for um end of
life care. This was someone that we um
designed a pathway where someone would
be able to have less training. They
would be more assisting with the um with
the end of life you know provider and
it's a a place for also uh people to
volunteer and such. The next slide gives
a little bit of an overview in the
training of that role. So, completion of
a space attendant uh training um uh
completion of psychedelic sitter support
training like the Zeno project and the
actual the end of life training that
we're talking about. So, just to remind
us when we're talking about
competencies, it's not just for um
providers and facilitators but also for
space attendant.
Okay. And next slide. So, um, that's all
really just an introduction to what
we're going to do today, which is
explore educational competencies. And,
uh, Jen's going to start going over
dactic horse training, and then I'm
going to discuss, um, how that may
follow up into practicum. So,
introducing Jen Clement.
>> Hey, everyone.
Yes. Jonathan, can you bring up the
slides, please?
>> Yeah. Let's see.
Okay. Are those showing?
>> Yes. Okay. Coming. Okay. Can everybody
see that?
>> Okay. All right.
>> So, as you heard from Larry, we're
proposing a New Mexico adjunct training
in end of life psychedelic care. Um,
this is a supplement to the state's
psilocybin facilitator training. It's
not to mean to replace it um or create
any track, separate track. Um the
curriculum is modeled in part on um the
end of life psychedelic care program
that's run by Christine Caldwell. I
believe she's on the call. So we can
also have her available to answer
questions. So really establishes uh
adapts and establish end of life care
principles to specific demands of of
psilocybin assisted care.
Okay. Um and the idea is that um
training organizations should really
have flexibility in how they deliver the
competencies and module content. This
proposal is not meant to prescribe a
syllabus and not it's not we're not
meant to be rigid, but it's really
trying to set a framework for um
adequate assessment. And as Larry
mentioned, 17 or so hours of live
training instruction,
um five hours or so of asynchronous
content, including pre-recorded um
sessions, reading assignments, and then
some homework and quizzes and a final
exam.
And then we have optional add-ons like
practicum, supervised care, case review,
etc.
So, you know, I think the central core
competency, we're going to talk about
all of them, but really at the root of
it or the center of it, and I tried to
just come up with an image to to
describe this because I think it it
really says it all just to like see how
it's all woven together, is the ability
to be self-reflective
and the ability to have an understanding
of one's own relationship with death,
grief, and spirituality. I think we all
agreed on this and we're trying to
figure out like is this a one separate
core competency or is this like kind of
woven in and it could be essentially yes
it is the core competency but it's also
reflected in all of the modules that
you'll see. So I I called this the
anchor um this anchors all of those
eight the eight practice domains and
it's foundational for effective end of
life care
in this psilocybin context.
So I'm going to go through eight of
them. So here's the first four. I
couldn't fit them all on one slide, so I
broke it into two slides. Um, first of
all, you know, understanding the
client's mindset when they're undergoing
serious illness and end of life care.
That's the that's the first one. Second
is medical complexity and safety
considerations for psilocybin and
ketamine and end of life care since
ketamine is currently legal and will be
is is one um option that uh end of life
patients can pursue. The third one is
spiritual assessment and meaning making.
And the fourth is grief, loss and
bereiement.
Okay, next slide please.
Number five is family engagement and
relational systems.
Then we have adapting facilitation for
serious illness and end of life context.
So adapting psilocybin facilitation.
And then uh seven is ethics, culture and
equity and informed consent in end of
life psilocybin care. And then finally,
uh, interdisciplinary collaboration,
self-awareness or being reflective, and
sustainable practices, how to keep from
burning out, for example.
Okay, so the curriculum that um we're
looking at is is really building upon
all of these competencies and assessing
assessing them. And I know this is a
little hard to read. There's a lot of
words here. I try to make this as
specific as possible. Actually, could
you push the plus sign? Click on the
plus sign. Jonathan, thank you. So for
the first competency
um we wanted to build an um time for a
session around the the first one
understanding the client mindset. So
this one would be exploring how um
illnesses, mortality awareness, fear,
identity shifts and anticipatory grief
as well as existential distress um shape
the client experience and how that
influences psychedelic care. Um two
learning objectives here are identifying
uh common Oops. Can you go up please?
One a little bit. Yeah. So we want um
participants to be able be able to
identify common physical, psychological,
existential and spiritual concerns
experienced by indiv those serious
facing serious illness and to be able to
apply an understanding of the client
mindset itself to support really attuned
person- centered psychedelic care.
Okay. and go down and then the next two
sessions are around medical complexity
and we broke this into two parts. So we
have two uh two two leads would be what
the first one would be a board certified
pharmacist um and then the second one
the session the third session would be a
palative care physician trained in
psychedelic assisted therapy. Um so this
would be examining symptom burden
frailty medication considerations
contradications and the need for inter
interdisciplinary consultation.
Um the two um the two or learning
objectives would be first to identify
those medical and pharmacological
considerations that could influence
psilocybin services in serious illness
populations
and then recognizing circumstances that
would require say consultation referral
or additional risk assessment.
All right, the fourth session would be
around spiritual assessment and meaning
making. Can you go down a little bit
Jonathan? Scroll down a little bit.
Thanks. So here we're introducing the
concept of the spiritual assessment and
we'd be exploring those approaches for
supporting people who are navigating
those questions of meaning, purpose,
suffering, forgiveness, transcendence,
and mortality.
And really the learning objectives here
are to conduct be able to conduct a
basic spiritual assessment that are
that's appropriate for psychedelic end
of life care. And there are as you can
see there there are many we all know of
some hospice uses some. So um we can
talk about that what that would actually
look like. And then the second one would
be supporting uh the meaning making
while honoring diverse spiritual,
religious and cultural perspectives.
And then the fifth session we want to
give time to a very important topic
which is grief, loss and bereavement.
And this is where uh we would be
exploring anticipatory grief, cumul
cumulative loss, caregiver grief and
bereavement and those ways that
psychedelic experiences may intersect
with the process of grieving. The two
learning objectives here would be to
distinguish grief related experiences
from depression, trauma and existential
distress. So how do you how do you
really identify what grief is vis the
others and then how do you apply grief
informed principles when supporting
people affected by serious illness and
loss not only the individuals but their
families.
Okay, next session description.
The sixth session would be focused on
the family and the extended extended
community engagement and relational
systems. So this would be examining all
the family systems, caregiver burden, uh
communication challenges, conflict,
strategies for bringing the others along
while uh we help the client maintain
their autonomy.
So this would be addressing um how do
you build support networks including
your family, friends, community,
professional caregivers. So in New
Mexico, we'd also build um draw bu build
an attention to cultural and kinship
structures beyond the nuclear family.
The two learning objectives here would
be first of all to co-create a support
network that includes the family, the
loved ones, extended community and
professional caregivers where
appropriate. And the second would be to
recognize all the family dynamics and
how to apply strategies for engaging
family members while maintaining
boundaries and that client- centered
decision-making.
All right.
And then the next session we propose
would be around adapting facilitation
uh for serious illness and end of life
context. So how do we adapt preparation,
pacing, setting, integration and support
structures because it looks very
different for somebody at end of life
than somebody else with a different
condition. The time the time is
condensed. Um, so for those experiencing
illness, serious illness and declining
health and changing capacity, what does
that look like compared to somebody who
is has uh PTSD for example? So we're
looking at a two-hour live interactive
session and then we'd be reviewing
preparation protocols, the journey
itself, integration and ato at with an
at home a home safety checklist plus a a
follow-up session. The two learning
objectives for this session would be how
to identify ways to adapt facilitation
practices for individuals facing uh
challenges related to serious illness
and then to apply the strategies that
would enhance safety, accessibility and
responsiveness throughout the psilocybin
care process.
And session eight
ethics, culture equity and informed
consent in end of life psilocybin care.
This was this is where we explore
heightened ethical responsibilities, the
power dynamics, informed consent,
cultural considerations, equitable
access to care. And those learning
objectives would be first of all to
identify ethical issues that are very
unique to psychedelic care that involve
serious illness and end of life
concerns. And then secondly, how to
apply ethical, cultural, and informed
consent considerations to end of life
psychedelic care.
And finally, the last session we propose
is all around interdisciplin
interdisciplinary collaboration,
self-awareness and sustainable practice.
So this explores interdisciplinary
models of care and the roles of health
care professionals, therapists,
chaplain, facilitators, end of life
doulas. We would examine counter
transference, grief, burnout,
compassion, fatigue, moral distress, the
emotional impact of accompanying
individuals facing serious illness and
death. And that obviously ladders back
to that first core competency, which is
all around self-awareness and an
understanding in relationship to one's
own mortality. The two learning
objectives are to describe the roles of
inner inner IDT members in serious
illness and to opport identify
opportunities for collaboration and then
to recognize how counter transference,
grief, burnout, compassion, fatigue,
moral distress can influence judgment
and therapeutic presence and apply
reflective practices that support
ethical and sustainable care.
Next slide, please.
And this just has the matrix this sort
of at a glance where you can see the
domain um how many hours we're looking
at and uh the potential uh profile of
the faculty who would be leading these
sessions what their primary learning
focus would be and then what the
suggested assessment are. So this is
just a quick and easy way to kind of get
a quick view of what's being proposed.
Okay, next slide please. And again when
we discuss we can go back to any of
these and take a closer look. So I put
together just a little um implement
implementation pathway. So how does this
look in process? How do we get from this
discussion to actually like putting it
into practice? So, you know, today we're
having this discussion. Um, we're hoping
to get, you know, kind of like a like an
agreement. Um, after some discussion and
adjustment and then we'd love to have
this adapted as a a training kind of a
training track. Um, then maybe we create
a working group um where we convene um
experts across palative, hospice,
psychedel, and psychedelics. And then
maybe we have a pilot where we um do
like a Q4 training with supervision and
then we do some evaluation. Does it
work? what are we missing? What do we
need to strengthen? What do we need to
take away? What's too long? What's not
enough? And then we um refine what we
do.
And the next slide. So again, like with
everything, we need safeguards. So this
this is something we all need to keep in
mind. We want to have supervised
practicum where we have those hours of
observ observed sessions with patients.
Um we want some collaborative oversight.
Um so nobody operates in isolation
obviously and then we want to make sure
this is really uh thought of as
continuing education. Um and we bring in
any updates into into the education and
skill building as possible as the field
matures.
So this is our our call. Can we we can
train if we can lead if we can train for
it.
All right. And that's that's all I have.
So back to you Larry.
I think there were some comments and
they were going by so quickly I couldn't
really see them. So I think Larry maybe
you can address the comments.
You're on mute.
>> Just to put in a context, um our our
hope in this meeting is for, you know,
and we we realize it's a lot of
information to come on slides, but for
everyone to kind of look at and see, are
we are we missing anything? Um is this,
you know, a reasonable amount of um you
know, hours that we're recommending,
which has been in that about 15 to 20
hour range. We have one comment from um
Jamie Beichi, who's a a chaplain. I
think we can call her a psychedelic
chaplain. Would it begin to include
something on the potential for
existential spiritual harm with pat in
the ethics section?
I would say that sounds like an
excellent addition.
>> I'm sorry I can't see the comment. Could
you somebody post it again or
um
repeat that?
>> Sure. Um, would it be good to include
something on the potential for
existential spiritual harm with
psychedelic assisted therapy in the
ethics section?
>> Yes,
absolutely. Thank you. Great one.
Well, I think what I'll do is is um you
know lead into a discussion on um on
practicum and you know and part of this
gets you know sort of intersects with
the training committee and the advisory
board and as some of you um are familiar
there's ongoing discussions about what
is the right number of dedactic hours
what is the right amount of um you know
practicum hours. the end of life
committee in in in our meetings had come
up with um 15 to 20 hours as being you
know dedicated training which um uh is
you know admittedly a lot of hours but
you know the feeling is that the areas
of end of life are not often covered in
other trainings um we haven't dealt with
where that training happens um um if but
one you know idea is that that training
could happen in in a core program and
again I know there'll a discussion
tomorrow about different um different
areas of training. Um the others
potential would be to have a separate
classes and there are courses around the
country that um have been done to offer
uh um offer that that training and those
courses are all based on didactics. The
other the other is to look at the
practicum and and figure out how does
this fit in the you know practicum and
as Jen mentioned you know in previous
meetings we've discussed that you know
this is an area that we we would like to
see people have specific experience in
the practicum that you know it wouldn't
be recommended that someone did a
practicum either with um you have
permission to do with with trainees or
for people in depression and not have
experience with working in end of life
care And so that was on the slide which
Jen mentioned having um supervised um
supervised practicum and again we're
we're somewhat waiting for the overall
model to develop but you know in the
discussions that we've had as a
committee the idea was that people
should have go through do a practicum um
with people potentially with attendees
then move on and um be doing either as a
co-f facilitator or working more
directly with an end of life and then
moving into um a plan for for
supervision.
So [snorts] the areas I'm hoping we'll
have a discussion and I want to mention
you know mention some someone uh here
Mary I mentioned Mary Kosamano is a um
is a psychedelic therapist with you know
many decades really of experience
working with end of life care and we
actually asked Mary to come not to do a
presentation but just to you know weigh
in if she has any thoughts or comments
about um you know about the areas of
training things we might be missing and
and you know that that difficult to
answer question about how much training
is needed and optimal.
Mary Mary just to any thoughts at this
point in the discussion
or
anyone else have thoughts you know
really on this issue of how much I mean
I would say before we get what
>> sorry sorry Larry it took me
>> I'm not used I'm not used to teams so I
didn't know where everything was.
>> Yeah, a lot of us have that issue.
>> Thank you, Mary. Thanks for joining us.
We really appreciate it.
>> Oh, I'm happy to. But, um, I did get in
late or a mixup of some reasons. So, I
didn't really see the whole outline, but
even if I did, it would take me a while
to like really take it in because it was
a lot. It looked really great. You know,
what you have, the little bit I did see.
Um so and I don't have um a couple
decades working with end of life um as
far as our studies go but um so I guess
I mean I don't I'm still unclear of what
this whole bigger picture who are who
are the people that are being trained
what kind of experience do some of them
all of them have end of life you know
that's such a difference in um what
you're looking at because if people come
in, so what are who's the ones that are
going to be trained?
>> So Mary, I think I think it'll be a
range. There'll be a range of people,
you know, initially um for the for the
trainings as we don't have a training in
um um in New Mexico, we probably will
initially be having people who are um
who are certified and get reciprocity
from other states such as as Colorado or
at least Colorado and Oregon. Um I would
say there's a range of how much training
people get during the programs in
Colorado. I was recently doing some
teaching with one of the programs and
because there's there's almost no
training like a couple of hours of
training and so in that situation um you
know as a committee we're recommending
that people get a separate training as
people develop New Mexico trainings and
as it's one of the four competencies um
um I think one approach would be to
actually include that you know 15 hours
or or what is decided on is recommended
in the in there. So there's there'd be a
range of people there and I think
there's also a range of people who are
um that are therapists or clinicians as
far as how much training you have.
There's people who are you know that's
been their focus. Um we know that
there's also end of life um you know
doulas and you know some of which may be
licensed providers others may become
facilitators. So I think it's I think
it's a range and and we're really still
at the point in this where we're both
developing the model for the whole
program and then looking to see where um
where end of where the end of life
training fits in. Mhm.
So I mean I'm not sure even where to
begin but I will tell you that when I
started um at Hopkins the cancer end of
life study we had only we had done two
studies before with healthy volunteers
and um and then we started the end of
life cancer and we were very small only
a few of us um on the staff. So, I was
doing most everything from the initial
phone call to the in-person screening to
a lot of the guiding to doing a lot of
the assessments.
And um it was so totally different than
anything obviously than the healthy
volunteers, but even looking back on all
of our studies, you know, with
depression and anorexia and um substance
abuse, it's it's unique in um what it
is, of course, end of life. And of
course there's a lot of overlap but the
thing that a few things stand out but
one was the intensity
of the process the screening process and
the preparation
because
people are going through this and you
have to get all their medical
information and and if someone's
listening and wants to hear they want to
tell their story and it can it's often
you know just harrowing and and painful
and so the story of their treatment and
then what their life has become since
and so often you know this huge um
change
so
we didn't realize that I didn't realize
that our team was small um and I you
know this is something with well with
clinical trials. Um, you know, you have
a certain time period you're supposed to
be working at it and getting people and
we weren't getting people for a long
time or very many and then all of a
sudden we got this huge influx because
we were allowed to have a travel grant
that made a big difference. we were able
to offer some um you know money for
travel
and um we got so many people and I was
the only one doing all this intake
and it's like you know we need people we
need to get going we haven't for a while
and so I was just going night and day
and I wasn't allowing myself
any break and I'd go to sleep you know
I'd do long days of all these intense
conversations
and then I go home at night and I dream
and get up and start the next day and
and I'm going to say this because um
I don't want anyone to get to this I and
I wasn't saying anything. I wasn't
saying I can't do it and I'm going to
back off. And I I really started to not
do well and I went to my doctor and I
said I need help and I'm not sleeping
well. told him what was going on. He
said, "Mary, you need to take you need
to take a week or two off right now. I'm
going to write you a script." Walked
out,
put the script aside and went back to
work. And um and then it it really um it
just it didn't resolve until I finally
said enough. And it was, you know, I
ended up, you know, working it out and
going through a lot to deal with it. But
I'm saying that with the intensity that
it can be and especially in clinical
trials. I don't know if you've been in
clinical trials, you know, we've got to
get it done. We've got to get this
through. We have time. We have the money
limit. And um this population more than
so many the importance of um being able
to um to pay attention to that.
And I'm going to say one other thing and
then I'll stop because I thought of this
right now. I mean I wrote it down
before, but I I had been a hospice
volunteer for almost 15 years when we
started the study as direct care. So I
um had that background and um but and
when I started hospice volunteering,
I had more time in my day and so I was
just on fire and I was so excited and I
loved it and I took on
a number of people. Um but I and you can
end up getting really um close of course
and I I took on this one of my patients
was this woman who I ended up getting
very close with her family. I was going
more than I needed to just because I was
just so um engaged in this and felt it
was so helpful. And after a few months
um it was a number of months before she
started going downhill and I had a
vacation coming up. was born away. And I
was like, I think she might die and I
can't go away. And I went to my
supervisor and I told her that and she
sat me down
and she said, "Mary, I just begun this
work." She said, "Mary, listen to me.
You're going on your vacation. This is
this is I don't I can't remember her
exact words, but basically you you can't
get that invested that um you know I was
just overboard with that. And so it was
a huge teaching moment for me to be able
to have that separation and really to
pay attention to that because I know you
all as caregivers as doing all work in
all the populations
how it can be easy to want to do more to
want to do more and and and you know go
out of bounds I don't I mean ethically
not out of bounds but in that sense of
what I was just saying. So, I'm going to
stop there for that.
>> Mary, thanks for sharing your
experience. Appreciate it.
But I'm curious other people's
experiences because I I'm
imagine people on this call a number
have been working with end of life and
um experiences that they'd like to
share.
>> Yeah, I think I saw Greg uh have us hand
up a couple times.
>> Greg, if you're there. Yeah,
>> Jen, this is awesome. Good. Like, this
is great. Um [clears throat] I'm trying
to get back to
the point I wanted to make mention of um
for my selfish reasons um from the
research and continuous improvement
uh subcommittee [clears throat] the
iterative evaluate and iterate use
outcomes data to refine the standards.
Um we're currently in the process of
defining the schema that we'll be
implementing for data extraction from
the program. So any sort of mapping that
we can coordinate on here would be super
valuable for us.
Um one of the
things I would wanted to bring up about
training and education in
relation to
paliotative care and
specialization.
I wanted to make it um kind of highlight
something that Dr. Leman said um about
the 20 hours or the you know the
conversation about refining that um I
wanted clarification
if I'm understanding this correctly that
the
that's for the specialization
[clears throat] not for the core
competencies
of the training requirements for the
program. Correct.
>> Yeah. Are are you suggesting those those
hours before like a specialized
certificate in paliative care? Is that
correct?
>> Gregory, I say it's still it's all still
to be determined. Um, you know, the idea
was that if people are going to um be
involved as as the primary friend of
life care that they have that training.
Um um I there hasn't been a
specification about how that works out
as far as like getting kind of a
certification or such. Um I think there
may actually be some um and and Dom will
probably can speak to this that there's
some uh logistical issues of trying to
actually set up you know a formal
different pathway but uh but there may
be a way to be set it up as a
recommended requirement
>> for sure and I think like a lot will be
discovered tomorrow. [laughter]
Um but so in the in the context of end
of life care, we're going to have a
pathway for facilitators and a pathway
for practitioners. Each of those t each
of those categories of um care providers
are going to have unique requirements
for education and training. Um I think
currently the facilitator is sitting at
25 for shared therapy module simulated
patient with 5 hours facilitator 5 hours
practicum 100 so basically 35 + 100
whereas the practitioner is at 35 + 120
the main difference being in practicum
and then we what we haven't gotten into
is specialization of care and what I
think end of life or paliotative
um specialization should require its own
set like those 20 to 40 hours of like
additional special specialization.
Um
where are my notes on the four tiers of
support? Right? So in PQS they've
defined four tiers of support. So we
have a standard support tier, enhanced
clinical support, specialized support
care and then not appropriate at this
time. So if we define EOL as specialized
support and I think we might also like I
think there should be SUD
specialization. I think there should be
TDD specialization and I think as we
continue to add beyond PTSD and all the
existing models that we have, we should
institute some sort of like you've done
your general container, now you want to
specialize in this
this type of work with this type of
patient. I think that having these
specializations and deciding what type
of so if you have somebody that's high
risk they or maybe maybe we analyze what
what types of varity the individual
patient is coming in with and maybe
there's a container where a generalist
can handle
certain types of care and then maybe if
somebody is on like a higher end of the
spectrum of need then a specialist would
be required. tired. Something like that.
This is just like kind of been tossing
around in my brain.
>> Thanks, Greg. Um, appreciate that. Dom,
could you comment from the, you know,
your perspective, the do what's
involved. You know, we as an ELLL
committee, I think we're we very much in
favor that people do need some
specialized training and then that
should be both practical and didactic,
but how do we make that work with the
program? See if you could help us.
>> Sure. So um as far as that goes, I mean
it would be an additional kind of a
certification or endorsement um for with
regard to end of life as far as for that
training. Um and uh and I think that
would really be up to the the provider
to go through and do that just as what
happens now with many providers in
different other other different
different areas. Um and then um as far
as for the practicum side that really is
where with the educational programs
where they arrange for those practicums.
So they could do that where they are
arranging if somebody is looking at
wanting to specialize with regard to end
of life where they do that in situations
where that's the condition the patient
is going through uh and that they are
they have one of those end of life
experiences occurring. And so I think
that's something that just needs to be
arranged through the educational
programs with the current practicums or
with whatever practicums end up being
there. Not necessarily as an additional,
but doing it as a part of the practicums
that they already do. Does that make
sense? I I'm not sure if I'm explaining
it clearly.
Yeah, Dom, I think you are. And I think
that um some of this may become clearer
at the training committee. I I've seen
several proposals that are uh out and
about that'll probably be presented on
Friday which talk about different ways
to have um structured practicums where
you may start a practicum as a student
then you co-f facilitate and so we may
be able to work in in that context part
of what's written in some of those
proposals that I've seen is that end of
life is not the place to start um that
you may want to start you know working
with people who um either are other
trainees
um have things that are you know
diagnoses like potentially major
depressive disorder you know nicotine
use disorder you different different
things there and and not immediately
start with um with end of life so that
was that's some suggestions which I I
think make a lot of sense
>> and I I definitely agree with you on
that Larry and I think part of it too is
that's a part of why as we've talked
about this many times it's all a part of
the care team and so it's really you
know when you have the care team. The
hope really is and and really the design
is to ensure that there are people who
have experience and training and then
they're helping other people who are
helping to gain that um and so that you
don't have a all of the care team
members for example are all brand new to
this. It should really be that help of
of assisting people also to learn while
we're also assisting patients. And it
really fits in with the model that's
been discussed several times in which
we're trying to really emulate in a way
without you know specifying it as an
apprenticeship but really having that
sort of apprenticeship that is required.
That's part of the reason with that
practicum portion is so that people get
the experience under others who are
already experienced.
Thanks Tom. Let me let me throw out one
question to people just so we can maybe
have some consens. How do people feel
about you know the committee here
recommending that people doing end of
life care have had at least 15 hours of
training either in their quarter program
or in a secondary program. How do people
feel about that?
It's more for comment than voting, but
uh
>> let's see. Um I see Brenda has her hand
up.
>> Uh next,
>> um uh thanks everyone. I'm Brenda. I'm
the uh chairperson for education and
training. Um, I love what I'm hearing
right now because this is uh very vital
to um people that are specialized in uh
certain fields. And as I can see what
we're going to be discussing tomorrow is
maybe having almost kind of like I don't
know if this would be the right word
like a dovetail type of thing where you
know you have people that are
specialized in in training like um
substance abuse or um you know death
doula or even uh you know spiritual
contents that that your specific
training
is vital to adding on to the psychedelic
therapies with psilocybin. So, um I
agree with this. I I think that having a
um a supplemental or adjunct type of
training and education to what you
already have in your profession is
looking more like that because I think
as far as reciprocity goes, you've
already gone through an enormous amount
of training in your specialized field.
This is um uh the reciprocity part is
just to add on to the education and
training part with this. uh for the most
part I think we've been in education and
training we've been just concentrating
on uh you know the full course or
reciprocity and this is still being
worked out in training but I think that
uh tomorrow's meeting is going to have a
lot of topics that we need to touch on
as far as education goes but from what
my perspective is is that if you already
have training and uh in a specialized
field, you should be able to
add add on the psilocybin uh uh program
and training to what you already have.
So, um that's still uh up to um what
we're looking at for tomorrow's meeting.
Thank you,
>> Denali.
>> Hi everyone. Good afternoon. Um, thank
you so much for the presentation. Um,
and especially thank you Mary for
sharing this experience and lessons
learned. I think that's so critically um
yeah critically important not just well
especially for this population and I
think for all of the work um under the
program. So thank you for for sharing
that [clears throat] with such honesty
and vulnerability.
Um I want to make one offer and then I
think I have a question. So, I've seen
in um the department's draft uh
um curriculum requirements. I'm happy to
see billing and coding. Um, I think, you
know, one of the things that's really
important about accessibility in New
Mexico's unique program is the
integration
with our um [clears throat]
our medical system in that, right? Um,
you know, we have the opportunity to to
bill for insurance um if done well and
strategically. So I want to um offer to
if there are specifics that are helpful
to this committee and to whatever
certification
um PMHA and and healing advocacy fund um
partner to do a memo on Medicaid
reimbursement under the program and
there's a specific addendum on Medicare.
So um if that is of use uh
[clears throat]
we'd like to offer to make that
available um so we can help people
access these services
and then I think as um Dr. Leman was
mentioning and the logistical
like how do we make this work within the
department and the logistical
constraints that the department may be
under um
logistical and legal. Um I I understand
from a conversation that we had um that
you know there may be a hesitancy to
>> [clears throat]
>> um create a um
a a distinct distinct patient
requirements for end of life. Um and I I
I understand that perspective. I'm
wondering though and I think that this
is where um [clears throat] where Dr.
Leman was going right or I just want to
be clear if we know um and maybe we
don't right does that also apply to
creating distinct lensure requirements I
think it sounds like there's um pretty
broad consensus that you know
specialized training is needed but it
I'm curious if the department has a
perspective of whether you're able to
create
diagnosis or you know qualifying
condition specific requirements from a
training perspective
like could there be this carve out um
end of life certification and then a
requirement that if you're providing end
of life care that you have the DO
certification
>> Hi Denelli I'm assuming you're really
addressing it to to the department on
that. Um, and so, uh, with that
assumption, uh, it would be very
difficult to do it because it it becomes
very problematic from a logistic
standpoint. And, and just as one example
is say you have a patient who is uh, who
is a qualified patient under end of life
and they're joining a group that has
people who have uh, some of the other
qualifying conditions. So say somebody
else in it has you know treatment
resistant depression another person has
PTSD etc. then you would actually have
to ensure that you had practitioners and
facilitators who had all of those
trainings in order to be uh present on
that. So that creates some logistical
barriers and there's some other similar
scenarios that could create problems
with it. However, what we would really
recommend is that these additional
trainings and endorsements really be
something that that um those particular
providers really emphasize and that they
work on that. And that's very similar in
other areas of medicine. For example,
you can have a therapist um who while
they may specialize in one particular
area, they still actually are seeing or
treating patients in other areas needing
therapy. And so it's very similar in
that and not all of those different
potential areas of specialization need
to have endorsements, but they are often
recommended. And so that really would be
what what we would from a department
standpoint is we'd be recommending those
additional endorsements and can even put
that in the best practices and uh to say
hey this is something else that people
really should have as a provider to be
able to offer these kinds of this kind
of care because we do realize it's going
to be there. even within any of the
conditions, but especially within end of
life, you're going to have different
people who are going to have different
needs and levels of care because it
doesn't mean also that somebody who has
one condition may not also qualify on
one or multiple of the other four
conditions. And so, um, that's that's
one of those, uh, ideas. I hope that
helps. Um, so yes, Denali, I see in your
in the chat. Yeah. So, it would be
better for it to be an endorsement that
is required through best practices, not
necessarily through regulations. As we
look at it, I hope that helps clarify
it. But still really, you know, we want
people to make sure that they have the
ability to care for people. But, uh, it
also we're we're talking a wide range of
potential um, you know, potential needs
quite frankly.
Dom, Mrs. Larry, that that to me that's
super helpful. I mean, one way I think
about that is right now this is an end
of life committee, but once this moves
forward, maybe there needs to be a New
Mexico end of life psychedelic, you
know, practically
a governmental point of view, but come
from a professional organization, which
is how it happens in a lot of
healthcare.
>> Exactly, Larry. You you you hit on it
perfectly.
I think Jamie, I think you're Let's see
if I see who's next here.
>> Greg up next.
>> Yeah, Greg. Sorry.
>> Got to deal with me first.
>> Love to deal with you, Greg.
>> Thanks, man. Um, I love to deal with
you, Larry. I wish I saw more of you.
Um, couple things. I'm going to flip my
my statement and cuz I do want to get
back to the committee chair's request
for input. Um but first just trailing on
the last two bits of conversation that
like I think we act like this last 10
minutes I think we got somewhere.
[laughter] Um but I want to throw out
that we consider like Brenda was
touching on adding reciprocity for field
specifications. So if somebody is an
expert in a domain such as paliative
care, somebody that's been working with
end of life for decades or whatever,
that person just needs to go through the
standard core training for the
psychedelic care and then they are they
like their existing credential
authorizes them or credentials them or
has you know you like puts them in the
I'm this kind of therapist zone, however
the department regulates that. But I
think the idea of
um leaving it to the open market is
probably more in the best interest of
of the department from their from their
regulatory stance. [clears throat] But
getting back to Dr. Leman's request. Um,
I was thinking that
I wanted to clarify if you were
suggesting that we include those
specification hours as a chunk of the
core practicum and core training or
would those be an like a kind of a
separate piece added on? So like we have
generalized care and generalized care
should care cover the domains that
currently exist in the program but as it
grows it's going to be like a lighter
touch on each of those things. So like
do we have majors like can I be go into
a program am I going to major in end of
life with a minor in PTSD or you know
like so just kind of fleshing out your
your request and question there. Um, I
think I would sit in the camp of keeping
them outside of the core.
Like I would like the core to be as as
robust as possible and specialties to be
outside of that. Personally,
>> Greg, I'd be happy to share my my
thoughts on that. I I think that we have
we realize initially we're going to be
having many people here by reciprocity
because we don't have a New Mexico
training, but once we have a a New
Mexico training, um I I would actually
advocate the opposite. I I would
advocate given that we have four
criteria that it would be appropriate to
include those 15 hours to to have
everybody
trained in that. Um but I think in the
meantime I think we will have people
coming from who who don't have that
training in their core and we need to
get that as a as a as a specialty sort
of add-on. So like we insist that the
core generalized training include 15
hours of end of life
uh focus
as well as the other domains and like
the I'm almost seeing this as baking
like insisting that we bake in the four
domains of care into the generalized
curriculum.
Yeah, I I I think that's going to be I
know this conversation will be continued
tomorrow because I know but I think that
um end of life might make more sense to
bacon. I'm not sure for instance that
that everyone is going to be trained or
want to be doing um you know substance
use disorders and so it may vary for
different you know for for different
conditions. I think there needs to be
flexibility too as as you mentioned um
let's say somebody came from uh Colorado
had a program that didn't have end of
life but they completed the Colorado
program and they're a paliative care
therapist I I think it would be they
should be able to to test out of those
hours and I think that's really what um
you know what what the intent has been
for the program that if you have
training you can test out in this I
think the question is is Is it part of
core training or not?
>> I is it. So, do we offer test out and
credential out or is it mandatory test?
>> Can you credential out of something?
>> Question mark for tomorrow.
>> Yeah. Yeah. No, I I think Donna has has
a has a com. I mean, it sort of depends
what you're doing. This comes up some
somewhat in other areas of medicine. In
other words, like people's create some
special training you have to do for
buprenorphine for primary care, but they
don't require an addiction medicine
specialist to do that. I mean, I think
that if someone actually is a a
paliative care therapist, it seems like
they shouldn't um necessarily have to if
they're a palative care specialist and
they're a psilocybin
trained uh provider, I don't know that
they should have to do an extra
training, but that that would be my take
on that. And those are the people that
we really really want to support. So
anyways, thank you.
>> All right, Jamie, your mic's been
enabled.
>> Thank you. I'm appreciating the uh
conversation and just have a a few quick
thoughts. One is that I
I think that um a lot of the curriculum
that Jen presented I would hope would
overlap with New Mexico's general
program like the uh the ethics and
spirituality sections and meaning making
and um I mean a lot of it seems pretty
foundational for any kind of psychedelic
care. So, I wonder if you know the the
parts that are very very specific to end
of life were were kind of uh pulled out
of the curriculum. I wonder how many
hours that would be. Um, and I would
advocate for a lot of what you
presented, Jen, to be included for
everyone, whether or not they're working
with end of life because there's, you
know, potential for spiritual harm
working with people with PTSD or with
depression or with any of these um other
indications. And then I just had a a
question about um about prescribers.
So in my in my experience of you know
what unfolded in Colorado as someone who
was who contributed to the Colorado
rules when I was living there and
developed a training program that tried
to accommodate you know the needs of
prescribers. I'm just wondering um how
this will actually look
in in real time. So a prescriber would
would ultimately ultimately be
responsible for prescribing the medicine
and for the oversight of safety. Is that
my understanding? And that you know
there's just such a broad range of
acuity when it comes to people that
might qualify as an end of life uh care
seeker.
So there's a big difference between
someone that receives like a low a very
low grade breast cancer diagnosis and
mortality is just in their in their um
you know in their a in their awareness
and they want to explore it and then
someone who has very acute uh needs and
perhaps is even hospitalized. So I see
uh Greg you're saying that there's no
prescription. So,
um, well, maybe medical evaluation is
what I'm getting at then. But just I'm
wondering in terms of, you know,
prescribers like how or just the
whoever's providing the medical
oversight when there's physical acuity
and not just mental mental health
acuity, then how you know that seems
like that might drive some of the
decision- making about who can be in the
room and who's responsible. So, those
are my comments. Thank you.
Thank you, Jamie. Christine, your mic's
been enabled.
>> Hi all. Thank you so much, Jen. That was
great. Hi, Mary and Mike. Mary, good to
hear you. I guess um this has been a
really great and thoughtful
conversation. Certainly raises a lot
more questions than um I know I had
initially thought about. I really
appreciate that. But I do want to make a
this is just my opinions, but um I do
like the idea of an adjunct training for
end of life and not folding it in. And
I'll tell you in part because uh you
know Mary hit the nail on the head. Um
this tr this work these clients have a
very different mindset.
Hence there needs to be a unique uh set
of practice and training considerations.
So most people and again this is my
opinion um oh not most people um the
people who do work in palative care are
special
and I don't think there's a lot of
people who really can um handle it that
well and I would say leave it to them to
do the core the rest pro the core and
then take the extra training. I can tell
you as a nonprofit my courses are don't
cost that much money. Um, so I, you
know, I I don't know. I would I would be
in favor of um, uh, adjunct training.
And then to Jaime's point, I guess when
I think about the way we teach our
spirituality course, it's very specific
to end of life existential distress and
spiritual discre distress.
And um I know you said you helped to
create a curriculum, but in the training
organization I teach for they don't go
into this level of detail or
competencies regarding spirituality.
So thank you. That's what I wanted to
say.
Thank you. And I see Michael's hand up
next.
Thank you. Um
yes has really been stimulating
conversation mostly focused on these
different medical systems
and um
you know I as I've been listening I I
ponder um you know the palative people
and hospice people are so used to being
with people who are dying and so
compassionate. I've [clears throat]
worked with them with several patients
that helped them across in the past and
saw how they worked and they certainly
come into it with a lot of love and
attention.
But then when when you throw in the
psilocybin um way of working with
sitting or attending to a person, I
sometimes wonder if
the nondirective approach might be a
little challenging for them in that they
are often in a position of wanting to
help and ease suffering. ing when
sometimes in the medicine space
um and they need to be left alone and
that is sometimes where the healing
happens.
And so in some ways I'm sitting here
feeling like we've got this round thing
that we're trying to fit in a a square
box. And I'm just wondering if there can
be some training around how to be
present and compassion and human and and
lean into the uncomfortableness
instead of wanting to fix it or change
it. Because from my experience in the
medicine space, um
that's what we learn is how to be
comfortable in the uncomfortableness
and not intervene and um not to direct.
And perhaps this is some other category
that hasn't been, you know, talked about
yet. and and even the act of being quiet
and still for five straight hours for
the people that don't say a word
and how to hold that presence and
confidence and humanity um and allow
that process to work because that's also
where the healing shows up. So there's a
big focus on all these other medical
you know areas but from my experience
and I've also worked with you know
people who
well I've said no to people and not
wanted to I didn't think a journey would
be beneficial because they were so close
to death. Um so who makes that call? um
you know and on the other spect end of
the spectrum is the person that just got
diagnosis he may not die for five years
and so in the actual journey Dade do we
need all these doctors in the room um
and nurses and you know um are they
going to be on a blood pressure cup the
whole time? Yes, I see that mostly in
the pre-work and and assessing the um
medications they're on and any
counterindications.
But the last time I sat in a meeting
with this group down in Albuquerque, it
was proposed that one person come in and
do the pre-work, another person comes in
and does the journey day, and a third
person comes in and does um an
integration,
and who knows, maybe a fourth person
does uh you know, a few weeks later, you
know, a check-in. And that just seemed
absurd to me. the the importance of
building rapport, trust,
relationship
with with the person who is going to
journey is as important as the medicine
itself for a successful outcome. So
sometimes um from my view I kind of feel
like these things are understated
whereas
you know I I think that they're really
important. Um, so I think I've said
enough. Um, just food for thought and my
own opinion.
Thank you.
>> Thank you, Michael.
>> Sky Rivers.
>> Oh, there you are. I I am so touched by
Michael's
comment. I I just need to take a breath
as I'm sure everybody does. This
conversation is really heartfelt and I'm
so full of compassion for this program.
I wanted to mention something and if I
missed it, please excuse me. We talk
about the journey and then after the
journey we have integration.
But he brought up something. What if
someone's passing in five years or is
right on the cusp? My question would be
for everyone.
Would micro dosing following a journey
before a journey something that would be
appropriate for a patient? Has this been
talked about? And if so, I'm sorry if I
missed it. So, yeah, I was kind of
curious about that. Thank you.
Guess I'm calling myself. It looks like
I'm next.
Um I I just wanted to um first of all,
Michael, what you say really resonates
with me and it makes me, you know, just
think about some of the things that
we've talked about over the last few
months. We've had the, you know, death
duel is here. Um, you know, there's
there needs to be ways to be integrating
the end of life psychedelic care with,
you know, the broader broader time of
death and dying. I mean, I I know when
Daniel, I'm not sure if Danielle's here,
but Danielle and t talked about, well,
you know, these people are going to do
the uh the journey, but I'm going to be
the one who's there when they're passing
and dying. And that that speaks to me as
what Michael's talking about is the the
presence. That presence is is really
important. And I think like coming up
with care models that that promote that
continuity and don't isolate the
psychedelic experience from that,
whether that's continuity um you know
with a with the death doula if someone's
you know likely has six months to live
that that person may be involved with
the journey in there. Also, I think the
um the space attendants, you know, have
another potential of being able to
provide some continuity as volunteers,
but but I think the um what Michael
brings up as presence is so important.
>> I see Mary up next.
Um yeah, I um I guess part of
what my place in it where I see of um
having something to offer maybe um I
don't know specifically about training I
certainly could add things but mine
really is more from [snorts] Michael's
um where he's coming from and and it
hasn't been talked about and I I've
missed the beginning so I don't know how
it was talked about what is the training
for the psychedelics itself
and um how you know just like you know
what I said about how intense it is, how
much more time you need for screening
and prep etc. But just things like um
because we know with these you know
medicines that it can bring up really
dark really difficult um ex things and
sometimes things they didn't even
realize. So it was really important to
when you're you know screening someone
doing and throughout the prep the whole
time that these things can bring up this
and it can be difficult and is it
something you want to do at this time in
your life and we I did have people who
would you know I remember my first you
know woman who said thank me for saying
that and she went away and she called me
the next day and she I've thought about
it and no, I do not want to bring up
this. I'm too close to death and I don't
want that to be in my space. So, I guess
things like that that were, you know,
talking about um the very specifics to
this the psychedelic piece of it and how
that training and you know having like
Michael was saying someone do prep,
someone do journey, someone do
integration. I to I just personally um
disagree with that. It's that
relationship that you develop that um to
me is the healing and um the potential
for you know the therapeutic value. So
that those are um couple things I wanted
to say.
But so are you going to have two um will
there be two facilitators for each
patient?
>> Mary, this is Larry. There's um there's
discussion of different models. Um, one
one model would was to have and and the
terminology may be different than in
other states, but to have um like one
licensed provider and have another
person who um we call the spaceholder
that that may be more of a a hospice
volunteer with 50 hours of training. But
we're trying to look at ways to make it
um to make this as accessible to people.
And it may not involve having two uh two
therapists or facilitators, but perhaps
have a a spaceholder that would be um
somebody that's a hospice volunteer.
>> Um yeah, thank you for that. And that's
one thing that I just I don't know, it
has never come out much. I don't know
why personally, but we never at Hopkins
had to have two licensed therapists
um ever. and and many times the person
that I worked with was one of our
research assistants. um it wasn't just
any research assistant it ones who one
who you know had presence and whatever
but um and it worked and so I don't I
don't ever see and so there's so many
other qualities that make um that
someone can bring in um just because
they're um not a trained therapist and
the cost would go way down and um but we
never have so I just you So, want to
throw that out there, too.
>> Yeah, Mary, I really agree with you. I
think that some of that model comes from
clinical trials in other places. We did
think though that if somebody's going to
the home that they shouldn't go to the
home alone. And so we had the idea of
maybe the, you know, the end of life
psychedelic therapist facilitator going
there with the spaceholder would be um a
model that would allow there to be two
people um coming to the coming to the
home and not having two more expensive
people.
>> But for your for the not going to the
home, you might just have one
facilitator therapist.
hasn't been specified.
>> Okay. Okay.
We also I know this is um it's not
always the case now, but we also never
had to have male female and now you know
for the first number of our sessions um
or studies it was Bill and I because we
were the only two so it was male female
but that was never a requirement. Um, as
we move forward, we would not have two
males with a female, but we would have
two females with a male and and um, you
know, we just um,
often two males, two females, and we
never it never seemed to um, I don't
know if make a difference. We got the
same results when we did these different
scenarios.
Oh,
I'm just gonna reply and then I'll I'll
quit talking so much. But um you know,
Mary Mary, I think when when we think
about like the training, I think that
there's a likelihood of um that of
having people that are happy to be the
second person there as a spaceholder,
whether that's happening at the home or
not at the home. Um, and I I see that in
some ways as like an entrylevel position
for people who want to get involved in
um and psychedelic end of life care. So
I I think that may work there. I think
it, you know, I think there's an
advantage to having two people. So you
need to people need to take a bathroom
break. You don't want to leave the
person alone. So I think that, you know,
having um, you know, two people at a
session, but maybe one only one of them
a licensed therapist may be may be a
wise model.
Greg.
>> Hey. Um, [clears throat] a lot of
threads to pick up through this. Um, but
I did want to take a pause and just
recognize [snorts]
um, the space that we're in and the
presence of Mary and Michael. I'm gonna
throw you in there with the elders,
Larry.
Like the amount of wisdom in this room
and the amount of
like actual trailblazing individuals
who've dedicated lives to making this
next version of reality possible is
immense and I truly truly feel that. Um
to Mary's question on the facilitator
ratio, there is recommendation for best
practices and it's basically two to six.
So like 1 to three sort of with a
minimum of two involved and there's some
logic around group versus individualized
care. Um, and that is being compiled
into recommendation for best practices
and will somehow someway land itself
into the actual rules, but that's kind
of where the conversation currently
fits. Um, [clears throat]
to my knowledge, there has not been a
gender discussion. I think it's an
interesting one to consider. Um but one
of the elements of detail in research
data that we're suggesting to record is
therapeutic alignment and where
therapeutic alignment could essentially
have like if the question is did you
feel that you were aligned with your
care team? Yes or no like really basic
instrument
that could be that could lead into maybe
I felt like the energy wasn't quite
aligned with my gender needs for the
space. Um, and the conversation around
that is probably more complicated than
it was 30, 40 years ago, um, even 10
years ago. And I think that's probably
like an element of our evolution. Um,
one of the things that I think is
really, really uniquely interesting
about New Mexico is the program is
shaping up like it's a research program,
but we are going into the wild and
there's so much um IP from practitioners
like personal ways of doing things that
will have to be honored and allowed for
in the landscape of discovery. Um but
we're taking the saddle off to some to
some extent to allow for you know if we
choose to collect the data enough and
like people participate in the consent
to to extract their data from their
therapies. Then we have this immense
opportunity to like study this framework
in a much broader context than a
therapeutic setting. Like at Hopkins,
you have a start and a finish. And when
that study is over, unless you are a
specifically incredible human that works
way too hard until their health is
compromised,
Mary
that that that your study, the person
who's doing the study doesn't have the
capacity to be with that person 6
months, 8 months, 1 year, 5 years later
as they're continuing to integrate those
those experiences into their daily life
through practice and daily activities.
And that that inte that integration
process when we when you open up the
word integration and and extrapolate it
into daily practice and community
building and relationships that support
their betterness, their wellness, their
health through things that no longer
even have anything to do with
psilocybin. It's all of the sudden now
their health and wellness is about their
daily practice that could have been
kicked off from that moment.
But the idea that we can take
integration way past the clinical
concept and and fold that into people's
lives that they can take with them
forever is something I really am a huge
advocate for and I see being vitally
important to the, you know, progression
of this medicine and the way that it's
going to show up in the next decade.
But yeah, thank you everyone.
and Heneife, your mic is enabled.
>> Hello, good afternoon,
good now, wherever you may be. Thank you
for being here. Thank you everyone. Um
just back to uh the Larry's um
invitation and question around the 15
hours. I think that's great. Um and I
think this will come up tomorrow, but I
wanted to drop the seed here or revisit
it. Um it which is perhaps the way
things can be written is that you know
for the first year we're looking at the
reciprocity particularly for end of
life. Um and then we can revisit right
with the regulations and um
uh you know the certificates and and
requirements you know once the New
Mexico program is up because I I think
trying to create those guidelines and
rules now um feels premature. Um so just
wanted to to name that and thank
everyone for their hard work. Peace.
and Barack, your mic is enabled.
>> Yeah, thanks very much. Um, again,
Bareric Wolf um with End of Life Options
New Mexico, and I've been uh on and off
been able to attend these sessions. Um,
you know, uh, I really appreciate Jen's
outline of a a good training program for
this area. Um, and uh, I had a lot of
questions, but I've been listening for
the last hour and a half, and a number
of them have been answered. What I take
away from it is this is very formative
work at this point.
um because it makes sense not to get um
uh too specific before we have to um and
to stay as open as possible um to the
possibilities that we're going to
uncover as we go down the road with this
program. And I know that makes it
difficult uh you know for the
department. They got to get some regs in
place. We have to have some structures.
But I guess I come at this from a
perspective of uh
honoring as much flexibility as we can.
I think uh Gregory's last comments
resonated with me um that we're all
going to learn from the experiences um
that we begin to go through and to have
too many requirements and specificities
at the front end um I think um would
compromise the program that ultimately
evolves uh from this early work and I've
seen that in my career in different
areas like emergency medicine and other
areas where I was involved in developing
the very first training programs and
certification programs for EMS personnel
etc. Um it's it takes time uh to figure
out what really uh needs to work. I
think we also have to honor and respect
that some people have been out there
using psychedelics in their practice and
um you know u a lot of them feel good
about it. A lot of them were very
excited about the possibility uh that
are presented by our law um and by the
expansion of this. But we have to make
sure that we're honoring um that they've
been working in this area and we don't
want to put requirements on them that um
unnecessarily limit um you know the work
that they feel has been productive in
the way they've gone about it. So just
some flexibility in there for current
practitioners I think is important. I
also have faith as I think about our
cadre of volunteers and their various
levels of expertise and how they've um
gained skills and um appreciations for
the work of end of life working with end
of life uh people um that they will
self- select those who want to go
further and offer more services. And for
those that self- select to want to do
that, um, they're going to seek out all
of these adjunct trainings. They're
going to want to be as as good and
knowledgeable as they can be. Um,
whereas others who have been doing the
work will feel like their basic
credentials and their experience um, you
know, are probably adequate and we don't
want to compromise them. So those are
just some rambling thoughts u from uh
someone who's deeply involved in the
work from a bit of a different
perspective. Thanks so much.
>> Thank you Bareric. Uh Jamie, your mic
has been enabled.
>> Thank you. just briefly wanted to
clarify something that had come up
[clears throat] before because I don't
think I was uh particularly clear and I
also want to express just a lot of
appreciation for all the good work and
for for Jen's um contributions and
Christine's program curriculum that is
um really informing the process. Um I
just wanted to clarify that my
experience of um of psychedelic
work as a um therapist on the MDMA study
and then someone who's worked in hospice
for lots of years and paliative care
directed a paliative care program de has
I've developed curriculum in all the
these areas and what I've become
convinced of with with psychedelic care
in particular is that existential
concerns that in the broader field of
medicine might be kind of relegated to
end of life or paliative care or perhaps
trauma care um or just kind of ever
present with sil psilocybin. So that
[clears throat]
someone with PTSD might have a a you
know an experience of of fear of death
or um [clears throat] experiencing, you
know, death of others in combat or
having witnessed a death or I just have
a have a a sense that that that
psilocybin um tends to bring up these
existential, spiritual, religious
themes. And so I would hope that any
training anyone coming into a a role of
facilitator or um I forget the all the
particular names now but the facilitator
or the um the the guide um would uh you
know would have would have some base
competency in those areas regardless of
whether or not they're working with end
of life. And then it seems to be like
perhaps the committee could think about
it in terms of in terms of um medical
acuity. So that you know there are
particular needs for people that have
chronic illness and also have um are are
you know actively
anticipating a terminal diagnosis like
within a year or within 2 years. um
there are particular needs of that
population, but there are a lot of other
populations that also have particular
needs
that would need to be addressed. And so
for me, it seems more a matter of um
kind of acuity. So if someone has really
severe PTSD, then they would need to be
with a more advanced practitioner. And
if they're, you know, have like an ALS
diagnosis and they're only able to
communicate through, you know, a um
alternative communication system somehow
because they're not able to speak
anymore, then that would be like a very
high level acuity as well. So, I don't I
just hope that New Mexico um that you
all the Department of Health finds a way
to
make sure you're matching the right, you
know, skill level of practitioners to
the the folks that they're they're
present with. and that I would be
inclined after hearing a lot of other
speak people speak to include some kind
of death awareness and existential um
kind of spiritual foundation for
providing this care to you know for
everybody that that's going to be in
psychedelic spaces with with others
including that capacity to just let
things be and have that kind of presence
that that Michael and um others were
talking about and set healthy boundaries
like Mary was saying. So, thank you for
listening to my clarifications there.
It's good to be with you.
>> Thank you, Jamie. Uh, up next,
Christine, your mic's enabled.
>> Hi again. Yeah, Jamie, I I loved that
and thanks for the clarification. You
remind me of um you know I had hoped
that practitioner would actually be
responsible for a plan of care because
we know we're talking about and you
alluded to this there's a continuum
somebody just diagnosed somebody with
ALS with severe physical um acuity and
then somebody might be really close to
the end of life. to Michael's point
earlier, there are um facilitators who
are very comfortable going to very close
to the end of life and there's some
that's not they need to make that in uh
individual decision but I certainly hope
that a potential patient will have the
agency to make that decision pending a
medical clearance. Uh the second thing I
wanted to say back on the edge of
training idea um I've said this before
but I'll reiterate it you know um my
courses offer CES um for nurses and
social workers and um I will also this
course that I had thought about does not
have a CME but I will apply for CMEs for
it as well. So I think it's a great
opportunity for continuing education
credits which I assume will be part of
the requirements. Thank you.
>> And Greg, your mic is enabled.
I just really liked Barack's comment
about rambling thoughts
and I thought I'd share more. Um
[laughter] I wanted to uh quickly pin
the conversation about so there's a
conversation somewhere going on about
the need for mentorship and mentorship
model and then the need for um
uh reduced expressed and cost in care
and having practicum hours
exist in a mentorship model as a way to
support the labor force is something
that I wanted to just kind of like drop
in here as where it where where as it
applies to the context of paliotative
care where the context of allowing for
multiple people is a consent negotiation
conversation in the idea that other
people are going to be in the space and
end of life care definitely has the
story where individuals from the family
and the community may want to be in
there as a support system and may need
some sort of kind of off-handed
training, not official licensed type
training, but like you know preparation
training from the team care team. But
that ter care team offering
educated like facilitator in training,
practitioner in training that is that is
following a dual or a type model or like
a um [clears throat]
like I've gone through my training. I'm
going through my practicum. My practicum
involves attending births. Those births
are hours that can apply to my
practicum. that I'm seeing this person
who is my superior got like giving me
education through experience being
present and seeing and feeling the
impact of that space
um in real time with people who are you
know qualified to
uh provide the transference of magic
because that really is what Michael is
just talking about earlier, the
understanding of how to sit and hold
space. Like that literally is a magical
power that gets handed from individual
to individual and he didn't learn it
outside of a like in a in a controlled
box. It was something that was given
through life, right? So, we need to
honor that space and but putting that
second person in the room as somebody
that's going through training that needs
to have practicum hours like that to me
seems like a great way to, you know,
mirror an existing medical training
model that also manages costs and
provides that experience.
I had other thoughts, but I will um hold
them because I feel like I've been
talking too much.
Thank you, Greg.
>> Can Mary be?
>> Yeah.
Um well, first I want to thank you all
for your all your um comments and and
and um what you're bringing into this,
Greg and Jamie and Chris and Michael and
Larry and and everyone Dominic.
Um, I'm going to just jump into this
because as um, Greg was brought up, the
um, caregiver support person, I just it
was almost every single one of the
caregivers in our study at some point
said, "I need help. Why can't I have
this experience, too?"
And so, you know, I'm not saying
necessarily we can offer that, but I
know at Sunstone they were doing those
studies and it's something to keep in
mind, but you know, whether that's would
come about or not, just the importance
of the caregiver. Um I think some of you
mentioned this in some other realms of
feeling a part of it and understanding
because we did have the few that were um
didn't want that person their partner to
go through it because they were afraid
um of what might happen. And we actually
had someone, one of the partners, um,
the spouse was very jealous
when this person was so no longer so
needy to them and actually sabotaged
said
turned it into afterwards, you didn't
really get help and you didn't um have
such a great experience and that person
shifted totally of what they actually
how much they got out of the experience.
So, I I think that's something to think
about um the caregiver and how to bring
them in, however that would be.
And I'm sorry I didn't mention Jen. I
think I said earlier, I don't know, but
for that really excellent presentation
and outline. I want to thank you for
that. That's very thorough.
Thank you everybody. This has been an
amazing conversation. I really
appreciate the way people have brought
in their hearts, their experience, you
know, our hopes and um you know it's I
think it's been a powerful meeting. I
think we [clears throat] have some
agreement with some things that we can
start writing up, you know, writing up
as far as competency is and such and um
working with the plan for training for
for practicum. But um I I think all the
comments that hear about models that
support presence and continuity and I
think we need to keep that in our
dialogue here and um you know look at
look at innovative models in the state.
Um just to talk about something in that
realm. Um we are looking at the um
potential for a a small pilot at UN M
that would actually treat both the
caregiver and the end of life person. Um
it came up here in the past that that
wasn't currently covered under the state
bill, but it may be if there is
research. So we're hoping to provide
that that research to allow us to expand
the caregivers being able to receive
psilocybin.
So, thank you everybody. We're not going
to make everyone sit through a full two
hours. It's not like you have a timet.
This has been a really powerful meeting.
Um, we um should set a date for our next
uh our next meeting. I I know summers
get to be hard. I'm going to take a
quick look and throw out some dates for
people and see how they work. Um,
we've generally been meeting on Fridays.
Um, I wonder if, um,
Friday, um, August 14th, how that works
for people.
It's always hard in the kind of a Zoom
to get a consensus. Is anyone Is that a
bad time for anyone? is how does Friday,
August 14th and how does that work for
DOH? Do we have that time frame,
>> Larry? For DO, that would be fine.
>> Okay. Um, how about 9 to 11 on Friday,
August 14th?
>> That'll be good for the DO side.
>> Okay. If we don't hear anybody that that
has a conflict, why don't we go for that
date?
>> Okay.
>> Look forward to meeting. I'd like to
really encourage people here with
interstate of life to I mean I I know we
only have so much time but there are two
important meetings I'm coming up
tomorrow the advisory board and the
training committee a lot of what we're
talking about here I think will be uh
talked about at the training committee
so just if you have um you know the the
time and the ability to join um either
of those meetings tomorrow that would be
great
thanks again everybody
>> thank you everybody it's really
appreciate did. Oh,
>> wait. Don't let me get off without
thanking Mary. Um, Mary and Michael,
both of you guys for coming here and
sharing what you what you did. I think
that actually, you know, brought the the
tone of experience and heart and
presence into this meeting and I I thank
you both.
>> Thank you.
>> Yeah. Thank you all. And I'm really um
excited for you bringing this forward.
Have a great rest of the day today and
I'm sure we'll see many of you tomorrow.
Thanks, Tom. Thanks, everybody.
>> Larry, can you hold for just a moment?
>> Sure.